Guide to the Lourdes Benería papers, 1974-2008.
Benería, Lourdes papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Lourdes Benería papers, 1974-2008.
15-2-3934
Benería
2 cubic feet.
Correspondence, publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes subject files, conference proceedings, lecture notes, related to her career at Cornell University and her work concerning labor, women's work, gender and development, globalization, and Latin American development.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Lourdes Benería is a Professor Emerita in Cornell University's Department of City and Regional Planning. She was born in Catalonia, Spain and received her Licenciatura from the University of Barcelona in 1961. She studied economics at Columbia University, earning a M.Ph. in 1974 and a Ph.D.in 1975. She was an assistant and then associate professor at Rutgers University from 1975-1986. She began teaching at Cornell University's Department of City and Regional Planning in 1987 with a dual appointment in Gender, Feminist and Sexuality Studies. She was the first woman tenured in the Department of City and Regional Planning. Among other courses, she taught "International Institutions", "Public and Spatial Economics" and "Globalization and Development." At Cornell, at various times, she directed the Latin American Studies Program, the Gender and Global Change Program and the International Studies Program. She has been a visiting faculty member or guest lecturer at Columbia University, Rutgers University, the New School University and other universities in the United States and in Spain.
Benería's work and publications have focused on issues related to labor and the informal economy, women's work, gender and development, globalization, and Latin American development. This work has led her at various times to serve as president of the International Association for Feminist Economics (IAFFE), associate editor of Feminist Economics and The European Journal of Development Research, and a member of the Editorial Board of Economia Crítica among other positions. Parallel to her academic work, Beneria has been involved in activities of international organizations such as the International Labor Organization (ILO), United Nations Development Fund for Women (UNIFEM), and the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP). She was part of a team of international observers in Nicaragua for their elections in 1990. She served on the International Advisory Committee for the UNIFEM report on World's Women's Progress/2000; was a member of the International Advisory Board for the ILO's Global Programme on Socioeconomic Security (2000–04); and, was a member of UNDP's Directory of Appointed Experts on Poverty in Latin America and the Caribbean. Beneria is a recipient of the Narcis Monturiol Award given by the Catalan government for her contribution to the social sciences.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes subject files, conference proceedings, lecture notes, related to her career at Cornell University and her work concerning labor, women's work, gender and development, globalization, and Latin American development. Also publications and notes related to the Nicaraguan Institute for Women (INIM)and the 1990 Nicaraguan election.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Benería, Lourdes; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University.College of Architecture, Art, and Planning.; Nicaraguan Institute for Women (INIM).
Subjects:
Women in development.; Women--Employment.; Feminist economics.; Labor policy--Latin America.; Sex discrimination against women--Economic aspects--Latin America.; Women in rural development.; Globalization.; Elections--Nicaragua.; Labor market--Developing countries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Publication "The Crossroads of Class and Gender", 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Documents related to "The Crossroads of Class and Gender": Book Contract, Correspondence with Publishers, Publication Announcements, Book Advertisements, Book Reviews, Correspondence regarding Spanish translation.
- International Association of Feminist Economics (IAFFE) Presidency, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  IAFFE Bulletin of January 2003, Brochure, Proposal to SIDA "Furthering Research on Cutting-Edge Issues in Feminist Economics: 'Gender and Aging'", Board Meeting Minutes January 2, 2003.
- International Association of Feminist Economics (IAFFE) Strategic Plan, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  "A Final Report with Recommendations Related to IAFFE's Future Structure and Sustainability" by Susan Kenny Stevens, Ph.D., Consultant with LarsonAllen Public Service Group, 2004.
  Email correspondence regarding the Strategic Planning Committee's Final Report, 2005.
- International Association of Feminist Economics (IAFFE) Consultancy and Ford Proposal, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Proposal to the Ford Foundation for Funding of the Strategic Plan Report by LarsonAllen.
  Email Correspondence, Invoices, Strategic Planning Committee Meeting Notes.
- September 19th Garment Workers, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  "This material could be interesting for historians working on Mexico (and maybe other social scientists). It's not easy to find it."-A note from Lourdes Benería.
  Newsletters, Publications, Correspondence, and Articles from: Interhemispheric Resource Center, Interchange/Woman to Woman, The "19th of September" Garment Workers Union, American Friends Service Committee-Listen Real Loud, Women's Project, Correspondencia (a Mexican Newsletter-in English, multiple issues), "Working Women and the 19th of September, Mexican Garment Workers Union: The Significance of Gender" by Teresa Carrillo, 1988.
- World Bank Consultancy Letters and Initial Documents - "Brazil Gender Review", October 1998- November 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  "Consultancy for the World Bank to review the Bank's programs on gender related to: education, labor, health, violence against women, and other issues in Brazil. Draft report included. October 20-November 18, 1988."-A note from Lourdes Benería.
  Correspondence, Notes, List of Interviews and Consultations, Tables, References, Draft of "Brazil Gender Review."
- Smith-Corona Study, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  "Smith-Corona Project: Final paper published in Economic Development Quarterly, Vol. 15, No1 (2001) and updated for my book "Gender, Development and Globalization" Routledge, 2003, Chapter 4."
  Project Proposal for "The Impact of Industrial Relocation on Rural Communities."
  "Planning Study of the City of Cortland," 1994, This report was produced by a class of 32 entering professional students in Cornell University's Department of City and Regional Planning.
  Newspaper Clippings, CARDI Newsletter, Correspondence, Email Correspondence.
  Interview Notes with laid-off workers.
  Revision notes from Economic Development Quarterly.
- Smith-Corona Study: Questionnaires, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Economic Restructuring and Community Development: Questionnaire for Smith-Corona Workers.
  Economic Restructuring and Community Development: Follow-Up Questionnaire for Smith-Corona Workers.
- Cortland: General Info 1, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Sample Surveys and Complied Results from the Cayuga-Cortland Private Industry Council, used with the Corona employees: Dislocated Worker, Occupational Interests, Training Interests.
  "Statement of Gary and Evelyn Allen", Former Employees of Smith Corona Corporation At a Hearing Before the Subcommittee on Labor... The Worker Adjustment and Retraining Notification (WARN) Act, February 23, 1993.
  Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, Meeting Minutes.
  "Social Cost Analysis of Layoffs of Smith Corona Workers in NY" prepared by the Midwest Center for Labor Research, October 1992.
  Tompkins/Cortland Labor Coalition Bulletin regarding plant closure.
- Cortland: General Info 2, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Citations in Newspaper Articles Database.
  Plant Shutdown Bibliography.
  "The Effects of Advance Notice on Displaced Manufacturing Workers:A Case Study" by Allison Zippay, 1993.
  Charts, Graphs, Tables, Demographic and Economic Data, Maps.
- Anti-Franco Activities (1960's and Early 1970's) 1, 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Newspaper Clippings and Copies (English, Spanish, French, and British), Articles, Correspondence, Documents.
  U.S. Committee for a Democratic Spain, U.S. Committee for the Carabanchel 10, The Public Prosecutor: The Court of Public Order: Madrid, The Spanish Ambassador to the United States.
- Anti-Franco Activities (1960's and Early 1970's) 2, 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  U.S. Committee for a Democratic Spain, U.S. Committee for the Carabanchel 10.
  Statement on the Carabanchel Ten by Eugene Stockwell, Noam Chomsky, Monsignor Charles Owen Rice, Henry Foner, Angela Davis, Edward Barsky, Ossie Davis, Paul Sweeky, Haywaood Burns, Eugene McCarthy, Bella Abzug, Ramsey Clark, Leon J. Davis, Salvador Luria, David Livingston, Albert Szent-Gyorgi.
- Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research Grant, 1983-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Documents relating to a Petition for Grant-in-Aid from the Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research.
  Petition for Grant-in-Aid, Correspondence, Acceptance Letter, Bibliography, Financial Accounting.
- Woodrow Wilson Application for Residential Fellowship, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Application for the Residential Fellowship, Correspondence, Acceptance Letter, Pamphlet for the Woodrow Wilson Center International Center for Scholars, List of Publications, Project Proposal ("Toward Human Development: Gender and the Global Economy"), New Fellow Announcement, Program Assessment, Address List of 1997-1998 Fellows and Guest Scholars.
- Report for the United Nations on "Apoyo A La Oficina De La Mujer," Nicaragua, 1985, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Correspondence from the United Nations Office for the Integration of Women in Development and Acceptance Letter for Consultation from the United Nations Development Programme.
  Project Report: "Apoyo A La Oficina De La Mujer"- in Spanish.
  Notes about the Project, Documents from the Republica De Nicaragua-Oficina de la Mujer.
  Report: Assessment for the Project "Apoyo A La Oficina De La Mujer" (NIC/84/W01) Presented to VFDW (Report of the consultancy mission undertaken by Lourdes Benería to assess the work plan to be carried out by the Women's Office, Managua, Nicaragua, January 1985)- English Copy and Spanish Translation.
- Illich-"Work and Culture; Meditations on Ivan Illich's 'Gender'", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Copy of "Work and Culture; Meditations on Ivan Illich's 'Gender'" by Lourdes Benería, Department of Economics, Rutgers University. (Paper prepared for the Symposium on "Work in 1984--Emancipation or Derogation?", University of Karlstad, Sweden, June 17-20, 1984. Paper published in B. Gustavsson, ed, "Work in the 1980's", London.)
  Notes on Illich on "Gender" NYU Seminar, 1/27/1984.
- Lectures and Talks, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Handwritten and Printed Lectures and Talks given at Conferences, Classes, and Events in the Americas and Europe, the majority in English, some in Spanish.
  Topics include Feminism, Gender, Development, Economics, Globalization, Reproduction, Women's Work.
- Lectures and Talks, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Lectures and Talks, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Lectures and Talks, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Lectures and Talks, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Lectures and Talks, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Lectures and Talks, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Lectures and Talks, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Lectures and Talks, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Lectures and Talks, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Lectures and Talks, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Paper for the Cambridge Journal of Economics "Production and Reproduction", 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Correspondence with the Cambridge Journal of Economics, Working Paper - ILO, Suggestions for Revision, Final Draft
- United Nations - World Conference of the Decade for Women on the theme of Equality, Development and Peace, Bella Centre, Copenhagen, 1980, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  "Reflections on the Copenhagen Conference" by Lourdes Benería. Introduction- "If you did not attend the UN Copenhagen Conference and were confused by the conflicting reports that made it to the media, you have one minor consolation: those of us who went to Copenhagen last July felt confused too." (This is a revised version of two talks on the Copenhagen Conference given at The New School for Social Research and at the Center for the Study of Human Rights, Columbia University, Fall 1980.)
  "A Feminist View of Copenhagen" by Irene Tinker.
  "Women of Europe", Brussels, March/April 1980 - no. 14 (A bulletin published by the Commission of the European Communities)
  "What They Did Not Tell You About the UN Copenhagen Conferences" by Charlotte Bunch
  "Set in an enormous glass topped forum on the outskirts of Copenhagen..." by Caren Grown
  "Forum80" Newspaper, Copenhagen, July 14-17, 1980 and July 21-24, 1980
- SSRC Workshop and Research Grant - "Household Dynamics," Mexico, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Work on the 2nd part of research for the book "The Crossroads of Class and Gender; Subcontracting and Household Dynamics in Mexico City" Chicago University Press, 1987.
  Invitation to the workshop on Social Inequality and Gender Relations in Latin America, Mexico City, 1983.
  "Subcontracting Links and Gender Relations" Abstract.
  "A brief summary of my research in Mexcio City" with Martha Roldán.
  "Entrevista Para Empresas Y Talleres" - questionnaire used in research.
  Application for Advanced Research Grant.
  Correspondence related to research grant funding from the Joint Committee on Latin American Studies of the American Council of Learned Societies and the Social Science Research Council.
- Paper for The Brookings Institution "Gender and the Dynamics of Subcontracting in Mexico City", 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Correspondence regarding participation in The Brookings Institution Conference on Gender in the Work Place and subsequent publication.
  Abstract and Vitae. Revised Copy of the Final Paper "Gender and the Dynamics of Subcontracting in Mexico City"
- Publication "Women, Households and the Economy", 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Correspondence between Authors and Publisher.
  Publishing Contract with Rutgers University Press.
  List of Authors of "Women, Households and the Economy."
  Advertisements, Reviews, Financial Documents.
- UNIFEM: Costa Rica/Panama Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Correspondence related to UNDP Office for Project Services assignment, criteria and payment.
  Original contract documents.
  Correspondence with Roxana Volio of UNIFEM (in Spanish).
  Appraisal: RLA/87/PRO2 Women's Studies in Central America Short Training and Perfection Courses.
  "Evaluacion Proyecto CSUCS/UNIFEM RLA/87/W05 Estudios de La Mujer en Centroamerica" (in Spanish) March 1989.
  "Evaluacion Proyecto CSUCS/UNIFEM RLA/87/W05 Primer Modulo Subordinacion de la Mujer. Informe del tercer curso." (in Spanish) Panama, October-November 1988.
  "Proyecto CSUCS/UNIFEM RLA/87/W05 Informe del Primer Curso de "Subordinacion de la Mujer". (in Spanish) San Jose, Costa Rica, April 1988.
  "Evaluacion Proyecto CSUCS/UNIFEM RLA/87/W05 Estudios de La Mujer en Centroamerica, Primer Modulo - Subordinacion de la Mujer. Informe del Segundo Curso." (in Spanish) Tegucigalpa, Honduras. July-August 1988.
- Summer Institute in Gender and Development, Halifax, Canada, June 1988., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  List of Invited Speakers, Resource People and Special Guests.
  Schedule, Biographies, Correspondence, Application Information and Application.
  Summary of Discussion Paper "When the Margins Meet: Thoughts Arising from Women's Economic Lives in Newfoundland" - Porter.
  The Revolving Chair: A feminist teaching strategy.
- ILO Workshop on Labor Markets and Structural Adjustment, Geneva, 1989, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Conference Schedule, Handwritten Session Notes, List of Participants.
  November 29 - December 1, 1989.
- Publication "Accounting for Women's Work: The Progress of Two Decades", 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Correspondence and suggestions for revision related to "Accounting for Women's Work: The Progress of Two Decades" from American University, Michigan State University, Institute of Ethnology - Taiwan and others.
- UN - Meeting of High-level Experts on Social Development Indicators, Rabat, April 1991, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Correspondence regarding "Meeting of High-level Experts on Social Development Indicators, Rabat, 8-11 April 1991" organized by the UN.
  Invitation, Discussion of publication.
  "The Measurement of Women's Economic Activities: Assessing the Theoretical and Practical Work of Two Decades" by Lourdes Benería.
  "La Mesure de L'activité économique des femmes: évaluation du travail théorique et pratique de deux décennies." par Lourdes Benería (in French).
- UCLA Conference - Learning from Latin America: Women's Struggles for Livelihood, Los Angeles, California, 1992, 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Correspondence (with John Friedmann) regarding participation in the UCLA Conference "Learning from Latin America: Women's Struggles for Livelihood", 1990-1992.
  Correspondence regarding paper "Contextualizing Women's Struggles for Livelihood: The Foreign Debt Crisis and the Social Costs of Adjustment".
  Copy of "Contextualizing Women's Struggles for Livelihood: The Foreign Debt Crisis and the Social Costs of Adjustment", 1992.
  Copy of Conference Program, 1992.
  Correspondence (with Jonathan Friedlander) regarding particiaption in the UCLA Conference "Structural Adjustment: Comparative Perspectives", 1996.
  List of Latin American Participants, 1996.
- National Committee on US-China Relations, Trip to China, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Correspondence regarding participation in study team on Economic and Social Development in China's Hinterland.
  Mission schedule and list of participants.
  Handwritten notes.
  Pamphlet from Xinxing Company Sichuan.
  "Economic Development and Human Rights in China's Interior" co-authored by Lourdes Benería, 1993.
- University of Wisconsin Conference - Sustainable Development with Equity in the 1990s: Policies and Alternatives, 1993, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Correspondence regarding participation in the conference on "Sustainable Development with Equity in the 1990s: Policies and Alternatives".
  Conference Schedule, List of Participants, Contact Information.
- African National Congress Workshop on Unpaid Labor and Economic Policy, Johannesburg, South Africa, 1993, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Correspondence regarding participation in the workshop "Unpaid labour and Economic Policy" organized by the African National Congress - Commission on the Emancipation of Women.
  List of Participants, Copy of "Accounting for Women's Work: The Progress of Two Decades", Workshop Proposal, Draft of Published Proceedings of the Workshop, Handwritten notes.
- Salt Lake City Paper, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Correspondence with the University of Utah.
  "Gender, Adjustment and Macroeconomic Models" by Cagatay, Elson and Grown - Proposal to the Ford Foundation, 1993.
  Handwritten Notes from "2nd Meeting", Salt Lake City, 1994.
- UNRISD Project - Economic Restructuring and New Social Policies, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Correspondence regarding UNRISD's research project "Economic Restructuring and New Social Policies".
  Project Proposal.
  Copy of "Structural Adjustment and Social Emergency Funds: The Cases of Honduras, Mexico and Nicaragua" by Lourdes Benería and Brendy Mendoza. Paper published in "The European Journal of Development Research, Vol 7, No.1 (June 1995) and reprinted in Adjustment and Social Sector Restructuring".
- UNDP - Human Development Report and Development Index Meetings, 1995 and 1996, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Correspondence related to contribution to the 1995 and 1996 Human Development Reports.
  Notes on Meeting of HDR96, April 22, 1995.
  1996 Human Development Report Proposed Outline.
  Endorsement Form for a new indicator of progress and correspondence from Redefining Progress.
  List of Participants of Brainstorming Meeting on HDR95, September 22, 1994.
  Copy of "Engendering Political Economy" by Meghnad Desai, September 1994.
  "Notes on the Outline of the 1995 Human development Report by Professor Antonella Picchio, Department of Political Economy, University of Modena, Italy"
- North-South Institute Conference, Ottawa, Canada, 1994, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Correspondence regarding participation in the "Expert Group Meeting on Women and Global Economic Restructuring".
  Questions for the group meeting, from Lourdes Benería.
  Meeting Information and Agenda, Participant Address List.
  Questionnaire Responses.
  "Expert Group Meeting on Women and Global Economic Restructuring, June 20-22, 1994, Ottawa, Canada, Final Report".
- Swedish International Development Authority Workshop - A Vision for Gender and Development Cooperation, Stockholm, Sweden, 1995, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Correspondence related to Workshop "A Vision for Gender and Development Cooperation," January 30-February 3, 1995, Stockholm, Sweden.
  Participant Contact List.
  "A Vision for Gender and Development Cooperation" by Lourdes Benería, written for the conference, with hand-written additions.
  Background information on the workshop.
  Draft of workshop result paper "Towards Gender-Equitable and Sustainable Human Development" and revision notes.
  "Individual Vision Papers Prepared for the Think-Tank Workshop 'A Vision for Gender and Development Cooperation'"
  Correspondence related to SIDA Workshop on "Gender, Macroeconomics and Poverty," May 31st-June 2, 1995.
- Universidad Nacional De Colombia Conference - "Debates Feministas Frente Al Nuevo Siglo," Bogota, Columbia, 1995, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Correspondence related to the Universidad Nacional De Colombia Conference "Debates Feministas Frente Al Nuevo Siglo: Mujeres, Democracia y Desarrollo en America Latina," (in Spanish) November 20, 1995.
  Conference program (in Spanish).
  Handwritten notes (in Spanish).
- UNDP Workshop on Poverty Elimination, New York City, 1995, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Correspondence related to UNDP "Workshop on Selective Approaches and Practices for Eliminating Poverty," October 30-November 1, 1995, New York City.
  Workshop Information: Terms of Reference - Consultancy on Gender and Poverty, Outline of Facilitators, Resource People and Sessions.
  An Annotated Outline "Engendering Measures to Eradicate Poverty" submitted by Savitri Bisnath, August 25, 1995.
  Bionote of Lourdes Bernería for UNDP.
- Harvard Conference on "Gender, Development and Macroeconomics," Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1996, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Correspondence related to Harvard Conference on "Gender, Development and Macroeconomics," Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1996, from The John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation and the Harvard Institute for International Development.
  Preliminary Agenda, Agenda, Dinner Seating Arrangement, Conference Announcement, DoubleTree Guest Suites-Conference Guest List, Participant List.
- MacArthur Grant Application - Sabbatical Year, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Correspondence with, application to and project description of the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation- Program on Peace and International Cooperation- Research and Writing Grants for Individuals.
  Final Report to the Foundation on the results of the grant-funded work: list of publications and completed book "Gender, Development and Globalization: Economics as if People Mattered."
  Foundation Pamphlet and Reporting Guidelines.
- 1997 UNDP Human Development Report Advisory Panel, 1997-1997 (Box 2, Folder 24)